<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<dictionary>
    <entry birthplace="Ireland" born="1736" died="1768" id="alexander-john">
                
        <title>
                        
            <csc>Alexander</csc>
            , 
            <csc>John</csc>
                    
        </title>
                
        <body>
                        
            <p>, a young writer of very promising
                talents, was born in Ireland in 1736, whither his father, a
                dissenting teacher at Stratford upon Avon, had removed;
                and from whence, on his death, the widow and family
                returned to England. After having gone through a grammatical education, John was sent to the dissenting academy
                at Daventry, where he prosecuted his studies with commendable diligence, and was afterwards put under the tuition of Dr. Benson, who had sometimes young students
                under his care, after they had finished their university or
                academical education, for the purpose of instructing them
                in a more critical acquaintance with the sacred writings.
                He afterwards entered into the ministry, which he exercised in and near Birmingham, but principally at a small
                village called Longdon, about twelve miles from that place.
                On Saturday, Dec. 28, 1765, he returned to rest, in perfect health, between eleven and twelve o'clock, intending
                to officiate at Longdon next day but at six in the morning he was found dead in his bed; an event which was sincerely deplored by his friends, both as a private and a
                public loss.
            </p>
                        
            <p>
                After his death, the rev. John Palmer of London published a work of his, entitled “
                <q>A Paraphrase upon the
                    15th chapter of the first epistle to the Corinthians; with
                    critical notes and observations, and a Preliminary Dissertation, a Commentary, with critical Remarks, upon the
                    6th, 7th, and part of the 8th chapters to the Romans.</q>
                ”
                To which is added, “
                <q date="1766">A Sermon on Ecclesiastes ix. 10.
                    composed by the author the day preceding his death,</q>
                ” Lond.
                
                <date event="work">1766</date>
                , 4to. Mr. Palmer has bestowed high praise on the
                critical sagacity and learning displayed in this work. It is
                some deduction from its merit,' however, that, in the preliminary dissertation, he favours the opinion of there being
                no state of consciousness between death and the resurrection. Of his talents, in another respect, a much more
                favourable opinion may be formed from the papers he wrote
                in “
                <q>The Library,</q>
                ” a monthly publication, conducted, if we
                mistake not, principally by Dr. Kippis. In this, Mr. Alexander wrote an ironical “
                <q>Defence of persecution, essays
                    on Dullness, Common Sense, Misanthropy, the Study df
                    Man, Controversy, the Misconduct of Parents, Modern
                    Authorship, the present state of Wit in Great Britain, the
                    Index of the Mind, and the Fate of periodical productions.</q>
                ”
                In some of these he displays genuine humour, not inferior
                indeed to that of most of our celebrated Essayists. He
                appears to have been a man of great worth, learning, and
                modesty.
            
            </p>
                        
            <p>
                He had a brother, Dr. 
                <csc>Benjamin</csc>
                 
                
                <csc>Alexander</csc>
                , a
                phyjwcian in London, who died young, in 1768, and was the
                translator of Morgagni “
                <q>De sedibus et causis morborum,</q>
                ”
                3 vols. 4to, Lond. 1765).
            </p>
                    
        </body>
            
    </entry>
</dictionary>
